Jhohev Sk

+1 (206) 593-9101 | sk.jhohev.us@gmail.com | linkedin.com/in/johev09 | github.com/johev09

SUMMARY

As a member of the Amazon Prime Tech Team, I design and build tech solutions that improve the user experience for Prime customers globally. As a software engineer with over 7 years of real-world experience, I have led several large-scale projects at Amazon that exceeded business goals and pushed the technical boundaries of distributed systems to support requests of millions of customers. However, my core interest lies in exploring the interesting low-level details of software and operating systems, down to thread and kernel-level operations.

EXPERIENCE

Software Development Engineer II

Nov 2021 - Present

Amazon (Prime Tech)

Seattle, USA

- Leading a 2-person team to improve customer engagement of a rewards program for Prime members with personalized recommendations.
- Led a 3-person team to design, develop, and launch a global multi-step reward program for Prime Day 2024, handling peak traffic of more than 10,000 TPS and driving over 240k orders and higher customer retention
- Improved response time of customer eligibility service from 5s (p99) to 50ms by implementing remote distributed cache with AWS ElastiCache (Redis) Cluster, resulting in 99% reduction in customer-facing request timeouts.

Software Development Engineer II

Dec~2018-~Nov~2021

Bangalore, India

Amazon (Retail Pricing)

- Received SPS Day 1 Award for my significant work on reducing time and cost of operations.
- Automated manual operations using Selenium Webdriver that helped operations team reduced a week (5 days) of manual effort to few (2-3) hours.
- Built automated experimentation tool that tested, evaluated and launched new configurations in minutes which previously took the whole day by operations team.
- Mentored and guided SDE-I to advance to the next level in their career.

Software Development Engineer I

Sep 2017 – Dec 2018

Bangalore, India

Amazon (Retail Pricing)

- Developed a highly-responsive Electron-based desktop tool (replacing existing slow Firefox add-on) with feature improvements like pre-fetching, multi-instance, zero-click auto-updates, etc., that drastically increased operation team's productivity from spending 5 minutes on each work item to just few seconds.
- Enhanced performance and reduced latency of a work allocation tool that processed GBs of data daily, enabling efficient task assignment for an operations team of over 200 members.
- Mentored 2 SDE interns on their projects, leading to full-time job offers.

Software Development Engineer - Intern

Feb 2017 - Jul 2017

 $Amazon\ (Retail\ Pricing)$

Bangalore, India

• Re-designed and developed data warehouse solution for report generation with write-heavy traffic of large-scale data of upto 1TB/day. Reduced query time from 1 day to few minutes (through efficient data partitioning) that helped internal operations team complete their analysis in days which previously took weeks/months.

TECHNICAL SKILLS

As a software engineer with over 7 years of real-world experience, I have designed, developed, and delivered several large-scale distributed systems of microservices that handle high daily traffic from millions of customers. Through these projects, I have gained expertise in every stage of Software Development Lifecycle (SDLC) and consistently focused on operational excellence. I have learned to improve code performance, readability, modularity, and extensibility by applying best practices of software design patterns. I have learned to make services more resilient and fault tolerant through design choices like availability zone replication, distributed rate-limiting / throttling, and circuit-breaker. I have built diverse monitor solutions for these systems through auto-generated metrics, alarms and dashboards. I have adopted efficient DevOps approaches for safely auto-deploying changes to production by following the standard practices of Continuous Integration / Continuous Deployment (CI/CD) pipeline, including Integration Testing, Stress Testing, Chaos Testing, OneBox stages, Rollback, and more. I have learned to find and fix performance bottlenecks in production using profiling services like Amazon CodeGuru Profiler.

Beyond work, I enjoy exploring the latest developments in Machine Learning (ML), Web Dev, and System Design, which inspires me to develop new ideas. Some of my skills and experiences are mentioned below.

Programming Languages: Java 11, Java 8, Python 3, Javascript, C#, C++, C, Lua

Java Dev Tools: Asynchronous / Reactive Programming, CompletableFuture, Netty, Apache Tomcat, Guice, Spring, JUnit, Mockito, Smithy, IntelliJ, Eclipse, NetBeans

Javascript Dev Tools: Electron, Node.js, Typescript, React, Express.js, AngularJS

Python Dev Tools: TensorFlow, PyTorch, cuda, Scikit-learn, SciPy, OpenCV, Open3D, Numpy, Pandas, Matplotlib, Seaborn, Streamlit, Conda, pip, Google Colab, Jupyter Notebook

Web Dev Tools: PHP, Selenium Webdriver, CSS Module, SCSS, Bootstrap Android Dev Tools: Android Studio, Retrofit, OkHttp, Butterknife, Dagger

Build Systems: Apache Ant, Maven, Gradle

AWS Tools: AWS CDK (infrastructure-as-code), AWS CloudFormation, S3, SNS, SQS, AWS CloudWatch, Amazon Kinesis, Amazon Firehose, AWS Elastisearch with Kibana (now OpenSearch), Amazon VPC, Amazon Route53, AWS Lambda

Database and Tools: DynamoDB, Amazon EMR, Amazon Redshift, AWS Glue, AWS Athena, RDS Aurora, MongoDB, MySQL, Apache Spark, AWS Data Pipeline

Caching: Amazon ElastiCache, Redis, memcached

Markup Languages: Markdown, HTML, XML, LATEX OS: MacOS, Linux distributions, Microsoft Windows

Other IDEs: Visual Studio Code (VSCode)

Version Control Systems: Git

Container Tools: Docker, Amazon ECS (similar to Kubernetes)

API Architectures: REST, RPC, WebSocket, Server-Sent Events (SSE)

Other Tech Stacks: MERN, MEAN, XAMPP

PROJECTS

PlayOnTop

- Developed a **Electron-based** desktop video player app with AngularJS to play Web/Local videos as a small floating player on top of all windows.
- Developed a **Chrome extension** to open YouTube videos in Picture-in-Picture (PiP) mode in the desktop app and including all default YouTube features.

Click List

- Developed **Chrome extension** *click-list* for chrome users to share links with each other.
- Hosted backend server with NodeJS (Click-List-Server) and WebSockets to notify changes to users.

DISARM (ITRA Govt Project NIT DGP)

- Developed Web application to extract coordinate information for offline representation (WKT) of an area using Google Maps API
- Simulated Delay Tolerant Network (DTN) by modifying open-source ONE Simulator
- Developed **Android** app to collect survey for research

Technoshine X.5

- Developed website to promote fest organised by university club CAD (Centre for Application Development)
- Used **XAMPP** as stack and had basic authentication for registration, login, and an online game Nethunt.
- Developed **Android app** for the same.

EDUCATION

Master of Computer Applications (MCA)

National Institute of Technology (NIT) Durgapur

2014-2017 Durgapur, India

on Sajonao

Bachelor of Science (B.Sc.) (Honours), Computer Science University of Calcutta

2011-2013 Kolkata, India

Achievements / Awards / Activities

- Organized 2-day Amazon Prime Hackathon in North Carolina A&T University attended by 48 students in 2022.
- Won 1st Prize in Hackathon organized by Amazon Retail Pricing Team in 2020.
- Received Retail Pricing Tech Special Annual Award for Customer Obsession in 2020.
- Received Extra Mile Award from Team in June 2020 and Dec 2020.
- Received SPS Day 1 Award for my significant work on reducing time and cost of operations in 2019.